Inventory of the Roger Mansell collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Civilian Prisoner-of-War Camps File, 1939-2010 (Boxes 25-27, 36-37)
  Includes research materials in the form of photocopies of rosters, reports, and photographs, as well as original memoirs, maps, bulletins, and memorabilia. Arranged by geographical region, then alphabetically by subject or physical format. Files relating to individual internees are listed alphabetically at the end of each subseries.
  - Japan, 1942-1945, 2001-2010 (Folder 25: 13-16)
    - Fukushima, 1942-circa 1945, 2001-2003 (Folder 25: 13-14)
      Includes photocopies of rosters and reports from the Red Cross and United Nations War Crimes Commission and printed copy of Golsworthy, C.R. "A Missionary's Love Story."
    - Hakone, Kanagawa, Kobe, Nagasaki, Saitama, Sekiguchi, Tokyo, and Yokohama, 1942-1945, 2003-2010 (Folder 25: 15-16)
  - Philippines-Santo Tomás Internment Camp, 1942-1955, 1995-2000 (Boxes 26, 36-37)
    - Apron, 1942, 2000s (Folder 26: 1)
      Photocopy, with list of signatures. See also: Box 37 for original.
    - Correspondence and notes, 1945, 1999-2000 (Folder 26: 2)
    - Magazine and program from reunions, 1995, 1999 (Folder 26: 3)
    - Memorabilia, 1942 (Folder 37: 1)
      Includes cook's apron with embroidered signatures of internees at Santo Tomás Internment camp. Also includes placemat and napkins with an embroidered scene of men waiting in a food line, circa 1942. See also: Box 26, folder 1 for photocopy of apron with list of signatures.
    - News clippings, 1949, 1955 (Folder 26: 4)
    - Notebooks, circa 1999, undated (Folder 26: 5)
    - Notices, camp rosters, and campus news bulletins, 1942-1946 (Folder 26: 6-7)
      Includes originals of Internews bulletin.
    - Hoffman, Margaret, 1942-1945, 1995-1999 (Folder 26: 8-12)
      - Correspondence, 1942-1945 (Folder 26: 8)
      - News clippings, 1942-1945, 1995-1999 (Folder 26: 9)
      - Photographs, 1942-1943 (Folder 26: 10)
      - Writings, undated (Folder 26: 11-12)
    - McCall, James E., 1945 (Folder 26: 13)
      Santo Tomas Internment Camp: STIC in Verse and Reverse, STIC-toons and STIC-tistics, Lincoln, Neb.: Woodruff.
    - Rowan, Jeanette West, 2000 (Folder 26: 14)
      Manila Diary 1941-1945: Thirty-seven Months in Santo Tomas Prison Camp. One compact disc, intended to accompany the printed copy of publication.
    - Ruane, John, 1945 (Folder 26: 15)
      Includes group photograph of soldiers at Loyola University.
    - Wilson, John, 1945 (Folder 26: 16-17)
      Includes original newspaper clippings of articles written by Harold N. Wilson.
    - Woodcock, Teedie Cowie, 2000 (Folder 26: 18)
      Behind the Sawali: Santo Tomas in Cartoons, 1942-1945, Greensboro, NC: Cenografix.
    - Wilson, John, early 1940s-1942 (Folder 36: 2-3)
      Includes issues of The Tribune (Manila) newspaper and a hand-colored map of Manila titled "Map of the Greater Manila and Suburbs Compiled by Surveys of the Bureau of Lands and Other Sources."
  - Netherlands East Indies, 1990s-2000s (Folder 27: 1)
    Notebook of research notes by Mansell.
- Combat Units' Rosters and Reports, 1940-1949, 1976-2008, undated (Boxes 27-29)
  Comprised mostly of rosters, reports, and related notes and correspondence. Original folder titles were maintained. Arranged in three groups: General, Air Force and Army, and Marines and Navy, then in numerical and alphabetical order.
  - General, 1941-1945, 2000s (Folder 27: 2-13)
    - Air Base Headquarters, Albuquerque, New Mexico, undated (Folder 27: 2)
    - B-29 pilots, 1945, 1998 (Folder 27: 3)
    - Executions at Camp Keithley, Lanao, report, 1945 February (Folder 27: 4)
    - Men held as POWs, Manila, Philippine Islands, Port Area Camp No. 1, 1942 June 13-1944 July 17 (Folder 27: 5)
    - Military units spreadsheet, 2000s (Folder 27: 6)
    - Missing air crews, 1945 (Folder 27: 7)
      Includes reports from 6th Bomb Group, 444th Bomb Group, 462nd Bomb Group, 500th Bomb Group, 504th Bomb Group, and 866th Bombardment Squadron "Taloa."
    - Officers at Corregidor at the time of the surrender of Bataan, 1942 April (Folder 27: 8)
    - Order of Battle, United States Armed Forces in the Far East, 1941 December 8 (Folder 27: 9)
    - Returned POWs, undated (Folder 27: 10)
    - Strength and composition of US Army troops in Philippine Islands, 1941 November 30 (Folder 27: 11)
    - Total US Navy Personnel reported as POWs, as of February 1994, by camps, by jurisdiction, undated (Folder 27: 12)
    - Unidentified and miscellaneous (Folder 27: 13)
  - Air Force and Army, 1940-1949, 1976-2006 (Boxes 27-29)
    - 5 ABG, 4th Chemical Company Service (Aviation), 2nd Quartermaster, undated (Folder 27: 14)
    - 7th Materials Squadron, 5th Air Base Group, undated (Folder 27: 15)
    - 11th Pursuit Group, 1940-1942 (Folder 27: 16)
    - 17th Pursuit Squadron, 1940-1946, undated (Folder 27: 17-19)
    - 19th Bombardment Group, 93rd Bombardment Group, 1940-1945 (Folder 27: 20)
    - 21st Pursuit Squadron, 1941, 1984-2004 (Folder 27: 21)
    - 24th Pursuit Group, 34th Pursuit Squadron, 1943-1945, undated (Folder 27: 22)
    - 26th Cavalry Regiment (Philippine Scouts), 1942 January 10 (Folder 27: 23)
    - 27th Bombardment Group, circa 2002 (Folder 27: 24-26)
      Includes draft of manuscript edited by Mansell.
    - 27th Bombardment Group (cont'd.) (Folder 28: 1)
    - 27th Bombardment Group (L), 1941-1949, 1976 (Folder 28: 2)
    - 28th Bombardment Squadron (H), FEAF, circa 1943, 2006 (Folder 28: 3)
    - 30th Bomber Squadron, 19th Bomber Group (H), undated (Folder 28: 4)
    - 31st Infantry, 1941-1945, 2000s (Folder 28: 5)
      Includes photocopies of the diary of Charles L. Steel, correspondence, and rosters. Also includes one compact disc.
    - 33rd Quartermaster Truck Regiment, undated (Folder 28: 6)
    - 57th Infantry, Philippine Scouts, 1940s, 1983-2001 (Folder 28: 7)
    - 59th Coast Artillery, Battery "F", Fort Mills, Philippine Islands, 1940 (Folder 28: 8)
    - 59th Coast Artillery, Harbor Defense, Corregidor, undated (Folder 28: 9)
    - 60th Coast Artillery, Corregidor, 1942-1945, 2006, undated (Folder 28: 10)
    - 60th Coast Artillery (AA), Battery "G,", late 1940s (Folder 28: 11)
    - 89th Quartermaster Battalion, undated (Folder 28: 12)
    - 93rd Bomber Squadron, 19th Bomb Group (H), undated (Folder 28: 13)
    - 131st Field Artillery, 2nd Battalion, 1941 November 21 (Folder 28: 14)
      Includes passenger roster for returning ship to San Francisco.
    - 153 MU Royal Air Force (RAF), 1945, 2005 (Folder 28: 15)
      One compact disc and one 3.5-inch floppy disk.
    - 192nd Tank Battalion, Company D, Harrodsburg's Kentucky Guardsmen, 1941-1945, 2008 (Folder 28: 16)
    - 200th Coast Artillery (AA), Payroll of Headquarters Battery, 1942 March (Folder 28: 17)
    - 211th Squadron, Royal Air Force, 1940s (Folder 28: 18)
      One 3.5-inch floppy disk.
    - 440th Ordnance, Aviation, 19th Bombardment Group, 1941, 2005 (Folder 28: 19)
    - 454th Ordnance Company, Aviation, undated (Folder 29: 1)
    - 494th Bombardment Group, B-24 POW rescues and crashes, 1945 (Folder 29: 2)
    - 500th Bombardment Group (VH), 1944-1945 (Folder 29: 3-4)
    - 511th Parachute Infantry, 2002 (Folder 29: 5)
      Includes news clipping and newsletter.
    - 515th CA (AA) payroll roster, 1942 March (Folder 29: 6)
    - 701st Ordinance Co., Aviation, undated (Folder 29: 7)
    - 803rd Engineers Battalion, 1945, 2004 (Folder 29: 8)
      One 3.5-inch floppy disk containing digital scans of Goldblith report. Printed copy available in folder.
  - Marines and Navy, 1941-2007 (Box 29)
    - General, 1945-1986 (Folder 29: 9)
      Includes personal narratives and other writings of soldiers aboard U.S. ships in the Philippines, including USS Luzon and USS Asheville.
    - 16th Naval District, 1941 November (Folder 29: 10)
    - HMAS Perth, undated (Folder 29: 11)
    - Karoen Camp, American Bunk order (Death Railway), undated (Folder 29: 12)
    - Merchant Marines list, undated (Folder 29: 13)
    - North China Marines, 1941, 2002 (Folder 29: 14)
    - Quartermaster Corps (QMC), Lamao Detail/Fort McKinley, 1945 (Folder 29: 15)
      Photocopy of roster.
    - The Royal Scots, 2nd Battalion, undated (Folder 29: 16)
    - S.S. Kirkpool survivors, 1945 August (Folder 29: 17)
      Photocopy of photograph.
    - Signals Company, Aircraft Warning, Philippine Department, 1941 December (Folder 29: 18)
    - Tayabas, detail in the Philippine Islands, 2000s (Folder 29: 19)
    - United States Marine Corps, 1945, 2002 (Folder 29: 20)
      One 3.5-inch floppy disk containing a list of former prisoners of war in World War II.
    - Battleships (USS) (Folder 29: 21-26)
      - Canopus, 1990-2004 (Folder 29: 21)
      - Grenadier (SS-210), 2006 (Folder 29: 22)
      - Maryanne, 1987, 2007 (Folder 29: 23)
      - Pope and Perch, U.S. Asiatic Fleet, 2001-2002 (Folder 29: 24-25)
        Includes programs and photographs from reunion and memorial.
      - Sculpin (SS-191), 1943 (Folder 29: 26)
        Roster of soldiers presumed lost.
- General Research File, 1942-1954, 1994-2009, undated (Boxes 30-32)
  Includes correspondence, memoranda, and notes. Arranged in alphabetical order by subject or physical format. Research in archives arranged by repository.
  - Miscellaneous articles, printouts, and notes, 2003-2007 (Folder 30: 1)
  - Bibliographies and research on book publishing, 1999 (Folder 30: 2)
  - Book excerpts, reviews, and purchases, 1942, 1981-2004 (Folder 30: 3-5)
  - Correspondence, 1995-2009, undated (Folder 30: 6-17)
    - Undated (Folder 30: 6)
    - 1995-1997 (Folder 30: 7)
    - 1999-2009 (Folder 30: 8-17)
  - Index to microfilm copies of recovered records, Philippine Islands, 1945 November (Folder 30: 18)
  - Index to Occupied Area reports and Foreign (Occupied) Area reports, 1945-1954 (Folder 30: 19)
  - Maps, undated (Folder 30: 20-21)
    Includes general maps of the Philippines, Japan, Guam, and California, as well as maps with locations of POW camps.
  - Membership documents, United States Naval Institute, 2000 (Folder 30: 22)
  - News clippings, 1945, 1992-2000 (Folder 30: 23)
  - Notes on USS Houston, undated (Folder 30: 24)
  - Permissions, 2000-2004 (Folder 30: 25)
  - Pending research file, 1946, 2008 (Folder 31: 1)
    Includes miscellaneous correspondence, photocopies of reports, and lists to be reviewed by Mansell.
  - Pre- and post-war documents, 1942-1949, 1994-2008 (Folder 31: 2-12)
    - Frederick Simpich, "What Luzon Means to Uncle Sam," National Geographic, 1945 (Folder 31: 2)
    - Women's Army Auxiliary Corps, circa 1942 (Folder 31: 3)
    - Introductory articles on Japan, Philippine Islands, and England, 1942-1945, 1998-2001 (Folder 31: 4-6)
    - Witness to the Trinity Bomb, book excerpt, undated (Folder 31: 7)
    - Memoranda to the Secretary of the Army, 1949 January (Folder 31: 8)
    - Newspaper clippings about the end of WWII, 1994-1995, 2000 (Folder 31: 9)
    - Exchange of messages between General MacArthur and Japanese General, Manila, 1945 August (Folder 31: 10)
      Transcript.
    - Photographs of Chinese stewards and Japanese envoy plane at Ie Shima, 1945 August (Folder 31: 11-12)
  - Psychological reports on POWs, 1991 January (Folder 31: 13-14)
  - Research in archives, 1996-2007 (Boxes 31-32)
    - MacArthur Memorial Museum, 2007-2009 (Folder 31: 15)
    - National Archives of Australia correspondence, 2002 (Folder 31: 16)
    - National Archives and Records Administration, 1996-2007 (Boxes 31-32)
      - General research on POWs, 2000-2004 (Folder 31: 17)
      - Correspondence, 1999-2001 (Folder 31: 18)
      - Notes, 2000-2007 (Folder 31: 19-22)
      - Miscellaneous web printouts and notes, 1996-2003 (Folder 31: 23)
      - Collection guides, 2003 (Folder 32: 1)
  - Subject file (Box 32)
    - Burma-Thailand Railway (Folder 32: 2)
    - Department of Defense, POW Appropriations Bill (Folder 32: 3)
    - Gripsholm, POW exchange ship (Folder 32: 4)
    - Hell ships (Box-folder 32: 5-13)
      - Correspondence, 1944, 1978-2001 (Folder 32: 5)
      - Rosters of passengers and summary of vessels, 1943, 1995-2001 (Folder 32: 6)
      - Arisan Maru, 2001-2004 (Folder 32: 7)
      - Kiska Maru, undated (Folder 32: 8)
      - Lisbon Maru, 2002 (Folder 32: 9)
      - Oryoku Maru, 1944-1983 (Folder 32: 10)
      - Rakuyo Maru, 1944 (Folder 32: 11)
      - Singapore Maru, circa 1943, 2006 (Folder 32: 12)
        Includes roster of British dead.
      - Tamahoku Maru, 1940s (Folder 32: 13)
    - The Liberty Belle (Folder 32: 14)
    - Nurses (Folder 32: 15)
    - POWs in Europe (Folder 32: 16)
    - War crimes trials, 1949, undated (Folder 32: 17)
      Includes records from trial of Major General Tasuku Okada, rosters, and documents regarding B-29 pilots.
- Videorecordings, 1945-2001, undated (Boxes 33-35)
  Includes 29 VHS videocassettes, arranged in chronological order.
  - "The Rover Boys Express Crew Story: Interview with Hap Halloran,", undated (Box 33)
    Two copies.
  - "World War II: The Atomic Bombing of Hiroshima and Nagasaki on August 6th and 9th, 1945, Narrated by Colonel Paul Tibbits,", undated (Box 33)
  - "Denny Dent and His Two-Fisted Art Attack,", undated (Box 33)
  - "True Heroes," ABC News, undated (Box 33)
  - "Liberation from Tokyo,", 1945 August 29 (Box 33)
  - "Ray Halloran, P.O.W.: This Week in Japan,", 1984 May (Box 33)
  - "Tokyo Visit," CNN Newswatch, 1989 January 25 (Box 33)
  - "Hap Halloran Interview by National Park Service in Saipan,", 1994 June 17 (Box 33)
  - "A POW Returns," Hap Halloran, CNN Tokyo, 1995 January (Box 33)
  - "Hap Halloran Speech, Nimitz Museum Symposium,", 1995 March 1 (Box 34)
  - "POWs: The Forgotten Men," ABC Nightline special hosted by Ted Koppell, 1995 August 1 (Box 34)
  - "Victory in the Pacific," CBS special hosted by Dan Rather, 1995 August 3 (Box 34)
  - "Nagasaki and the Days of War,", 1995 August 8 (Box 34)
  - "CAF Midland, Texas Airshow 1995,", 1995 October 1 (Box 34)
  - "B-29," CBS Evening Magazine, 1999 January 1 (Box 34)
  - "B-29," CBS, 1999 January 18 (Box 34)
  - "The Pacific Journey,", 1999 May 1 (Box 34)
  - "Hap Halloran Interview, Norfolk, VA,", 2000 May 1 (Box 35)
  - "Hap Interview #1, at Home,", 2001 (Box 35)
  - "Hap Interview #2, at Home,", 2001 (Box 35)
  - "Speech to CAF, Ray Halloran,", 2001 March 1 (Box 35)
- Sound Recordings, 1942, undated (Record cabinet)
  Contains 3 instantaneous sound discs.
  - "Hi-Ho; Prisoneers Recordings,", undated (Record cabinet)
  - "Words of Comfort, Rivan Oosbree,", undated (Record cabinet)
  - "Ravansky 12/7/42,", 1942 December 7 (Record cabinet)